to one one of the ends of the
permaculture movement so to the overall
aim is to create a permanent human
culture on this planet that lives in
harmony with the earth rather than
destroying it and what would you advise
young permaculture teacher or
permaculture activists anywhere in the
world to get into in terms of using
fungi as part of their power culture
practice well I mean this is why I write
books you know the books are much more
extensive than I can give in a short
interview so my solium running how much
would help save the world lays the
foundation and in the book is like a key
through doors which I hope other people
will walk through and elaborate these
concepts and discover that which
nature's already discovered we're rich
rediscovering that which nature has
already figured out and I'm hoping that
other people will be able to use this
knowledge to be able to elaborate you
know and be better at using these fungi
to help the help in the ecosystem one
thing that I think linear thinking is
extremely dangerous and when looking at
ecosystem design and many of the biggest
mistakes that are made I think in
science today occurs at the beginning of
the decision tree I think we have to be
multi-directional our approaches and
realize that in these multi-directional
approaches they have influences upon
each other and that we're part of this
large community of activities all of
which have collaborative effects upon
each other the problem with that concept
is linear thinking you want to find a
cause and effect and basically we can
have humans can have a cause that have a
multiplicity of effects that feedback
loops are infinitely onto the subsequent
effects the derivative effects and the
original effect of us and so this is
where you know we're first peoples in
particular in the use of sacramental
plants I think has opened up the mind's
eye to the infinite possibilities of
nature and I think so I monistic aliy
mushrooms have become powerful because
they do open up the floodgates of the
senses they do take you into
a larger dimension of Integrative the
integrative rules of organisms within
ecosystems and I know when I've used
magic mushrooms I get the same constant
theme is that nature calls out to me I
hear all these species all around me
rejoicing that I now am aware of them
but at the same time giving me the same
message the earth is in trouble don't
you know
can't you see do something and so what I
see is important within permaculture is
to engage the concept of natural
intelligence these ecosystems are far
more developed than any computer
technology that we can even conceive
through 3.5 billion years of life on
this planet that's been experiments have
succeeded and failed but we are here
today because we're evolutionary success
as is all other organisms it's time for
us to understand that the body intellect
of each species has within it such
powerful wisdom and knowledge that we
need to be able to bring that together
in a practical sense and what I see a
lot of people have their blinders on and
what's the analogy that I'd like to make
it's very controversial for me to say
this but I'm not immune to controversy
is that the people who are don't believe
in global warming I have a conch I have
a issue with the word belief how can you
not he is not like you're believing in
God or not believing God global warming
is a fact you know some people say I
don't believe in global warming you know
this is a long wrong language long wrong
words to be use but nevertheless they
use that and it's the same type of
people same subculture that I think
we're Flatlanders who didn't believe the
earth wasn't a sphere and then and then
Galileo said the earth is not the center
of the universe you know in the center
of the solar system and then he had to
fight that and I see the same sort of
conservative individuals who don't want
to see the progress of scientific and
religious thought holding back to the
old precepts and concepts which limit
says limits adventurous thinking and one
thing that is the pulse of evolution
is to push concepts of the edge and with
these funds I do so well is there edge
runners they're always at the interface
environments and they're constantly
experiment experimenting so if you had a
they totally homogeneous environment the
ecosystem will be managed by the fungi
maybe somewhat you know everything and
flowing and static but as soon as there
is an edge put into an environment then
the ecosystem has changed and that
interface environments with these fungi
come up with very novel and elegant
solutions to be able to put into
practice so we face a tremendous crisis
ecologically on this planet there are
some of us who can see it who believe in
it who know that we have to take action
and there are other people who are in
disbelief and this like being on on a
boat going down on a raft going over the
Niagara Falls there's a few people on
this boat are paddling like heck you
know to prevent us from going over
Niagara Falls and there's other people
who are sitting back saying oh it's not
important and unfortunately if I had my
way there'd be a division between the
people who are helping the people who
are aren't and the people who aren't I
wish they lived on a different planet
personally but be that as it may
here we are and I think our mission is
to convince the skeptics and this is
where I think I've done a pretty good
job at times is my greatest supporters
now where my former former former
skeptics and the fact that these people
who are so skeptical are now convinced
that we are on a path that's worthy of
merit
I think is a strong endorsement we need
to get more of those skeptics you know
on our side of the fence so they can be
active than thinking about the
consequences of their activities so we
protect downstream generations and
habitats from the actions that we're
doing today a couple of specific
examples of